A Guide to the Papers of Alexander Garrett, 1812-1848
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Alexander Garrett 1812-1848
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
860
This collection consists of 28 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was loaned to the Library by Mary Willis Pretlow McLemore on June 8, 1940 and was made a gift in November 1950 by her estate.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, 1812-1848, chiefly concerning the University of Virginia and its finances. The collection includes the Ceremony to be used in laying the corner stone of the Central College and a report on the laying of the cornerstone by the members of the Charlottesville Masonic Lodge and the Widows' Sons Masonic Lodge.
A letter from Thomas Eston Randolph to Alexander Garrett, 1829 Sep. 5, discusses financial concerns and mentions the imminent departure of the Randolphs to Florida.
A letter from Thomas Walker Gilmer to Alexander Garrett, 1832 Dec. 28, discusses the nullification crisis.
Correspondents include John Quincy Adams, Peter Carr, John Hartwell Cocke, Thomas Walker Gilmer, Thomas Jefferson, Chapman Johnson, James Madison, John Minor, James Monroe, Bernard Peyton, Martha Jefferson Randolph, Thomas Eston Randolph, and Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- P.[eter] Carr, Warm Springs, to Alexander Garrett, 1812 June 6., ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf. (Folder 1)
  Carr will not be present at the next election [of the Charlottesville Masonic Lodge?] and asks Garrett to confer "the office on some other worthy brother."
- Ceremony to be used in laying the corner stone of the Central College, 1817 October 6., AD, 8 pp.; silked. (Folder 2)
- Report on laying the cornerstone of Central College, 1817 December 1., ADS, 3 pp, with 3 blank leaves; stitched; silked. (Folder 3)
  A report from members of the Widow's Sons' Lodge No. 60 and Charlottesville Lodge No. 90. Signed by John Fugg[?], Alexander Garrett, John H. Craven, and John Harris.
- Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, to Alexander Garrett, 1821 May 31., ALS. 1 pp.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 4)
  Encloses letter that may be of some help to Garrett, although T. J. has no personal relation with Governor [Lewis] Cass and no acquaintances in Detroit.
- Certificate, signed by John Quincy Adams as Secretary of State, 1823 January 9., DS, 1pp.; silked. (Folder 5)
  Certifying that Richard S. Briscoe and John N. Moulder were Justices of the Peace, Washington County, District of Columbia at the time of signing.
- Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, to Alexander Garrett, Charlottesville, 1824 March 16., ALS. 1 pp. Fragment. Endorsed by T. J.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 6)
  Note concerning University of Virginia debts.
- Alexander Garrett, Charlottesville, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, 1824 April 18., ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 7)
  Sends letters [not present] from accountant of Literary Fund and from cashier of Farmer's Bank of Virginia. Asks instructions regarding a loan from the Bank of Virginia. Mentions Chapman Johnson.
- Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, to Alexander Garrett, 1825 March 8., ALS. 1 pp.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 8)
  Enclose Visitors' ratification of loan of $5000 from Farmer's Bank [not present]. Directs remittance to Thomas Appleton through Bernard Peyton of Richmond and Samuel Williams of London for columns.
- Alexander Garrett to [Bernard Peyton], 1825 March 9., LS. 1 pp. Copy. Endorsed by T. J.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 9)
  Garrett sends Peyton a check for $3000 [not present] to purchase a bill of exchange in London, payable to Mr. Samuel Williams.
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient], 1825 April 16., ALS, 1 p.; silked; photocopy; original in James Monroe papers. (Folder 10)
  Monroe sends papers [not present] concerning the mortgage of a tract of land near Milton.
- Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, to Alexander Garrett, University, 1825 June 2., ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 11)
  Asks if deposit to William Hilliard's credit has been made. Is sending catalog of books to Hilliard.
- Alexander Garrett, Monticello, to "My dear wife," Charlottesville, 1826 July 4., ALS. 1 pp.; photocopy; original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Folder 12)
  Announcing death of Jefferson. Burial plans. Reactions of Martha Randolph and the rest of the family.
- James Madison to Mr. [Alexander] Garrett, 1826 October 24., AN, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 13)
  Madison returns a check for $3000 [not present] "with his signature, as requested."
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1827 January 17., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 14)
  Madison returns a check for $12,000 [not present] with his signature as requested.
- Chapman Johnson, Richmond, to Alexander Garrett, 1827 April 6., ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Richmond, Va. Apr. 7; silked. (Folder 15)
  Johnson says that he met with "Mr. [Joseph Carrington?] Cabell" about the $25,000 loan to the University from the Literary Fund. He also tells Garrett that his "suit against Hay and Tuckerman was never instituted."
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1827 April 18., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 16)
  Madison "had signified to Genl. Cocke my wish that he would concur with you in arrangements for giving effect to the legal authority for a loan" and is "sorry for the failure of the first experiment." He hopes that Garrett's appeal to the banks will be more successful.
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1827 May 11., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 17)
  Madison sends an offer a loan from Thomas Jefferson Randolph as trustee for Martha Jefferson Randolph [not present] and "a paper drafted by Mr. Johnson" [not present]. He asks Garrett to poll the University's Board of Visitors by mail and as soon as he has a majority to take the necessary action.
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1827 November 3., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf, docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 18)
  Madison encloses a letter to John Hartwell Cocke [not present] and asks Garrett to deliver it.
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1828 March 4., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 19)
  Madison asks Garrett to send him the amounts and dates of any legislative "grants" to the University of Virginia. Notes, presumably in Garrett's hand, of allocations on both recto and verso.
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1828 April 5., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 20)
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett, 1828 December 11., ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked; photocopy; original in James Madison papers. (Folder 21)
  Madison thanks Garrett for his last letter and mentions "Mr. Trist."
- Thomas Eston Randolph, New London, to Alexander Garrett, 1829 September 5., ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; silked. (Folder 22)
  Randolph asks Garrett's assistance in disposing of two bonds; since Thomas Jefferson Randolph is a candidate for the Senate, Thomas Eston Randolph assumes he will be too busy to assist him. Randolph says that "young, healthy, well disposed Negro men will suit me as well as the money." He closes by mentioning that is his family is preparing to embark for Florida.
- Thomas W.[alker] Gilmer to Alexander Garrett, 1832 December 28., ALS, 3 pp.; postmarked Richmond Dec. 28; silked. (Folder 23)
  Gilmer mentions the bill for "the extension of our town limits." Most of the letter deals with the nullification crisis and related actions of the Virginia General Assembly.
- Martha Jefferson Randolph to Alexander Garrett, 1833 July 6., ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington July 7; silked. (Folder 24)
  Encloses a receipt [not present] "required by the Proctor" of the University of Virginia and sends regards of "the girls" and mentions Mary Page Randolph.
- Virginia Jefferson Trist to [Alexander Garrett?], 1835 August 1., ALS, 2 pp.; silked. (Folder 25)
  Chiefly family news; mentions illness of Cornelia [Jefferson Randolph] and Septimia [Randolph Meikleham] and her mother Martha Jefferson Randolph.
- John Hartwell Cocke, Bremo, to Alexander Garrett, 1836 February 19., ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; silked. (Folder 26)
  Cocke asks Garrett to purchase and ship to Columbia "two of Rodes' very best hillside ploughs." He comments on his poor health due to the recent cold weather and notes that in the previous week the temperature was twice at 5 degrees below zero.
- Chapman Johnson, Richmond, to Alexander Garrett, 1837 June 16., ALS, 1 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Richmond June 16; silked. (Folder 27)
  Chapman has received the draft of $5000 and deposited it in the Farmer's Bank.
- John Minor, Hot Springs, to Alexander Garrett, 1848 June 25., ALS, 3 pp.; silked. (Folder 28)
  Minor discusses his health and visitors to the springs.